XOR—Logical Exclusive OR
INSTRUCTION SET REFERENCE, V-Z
Vol. 2C 5-623
XOR—Logical Exclusive OR
Instruction Operand Encoding
Description
Performs a bitwise exclusive OR (XOR) operation on the destination (first) and source (second) operands and
stores the result in the destination operand location. The source operand can be an immediate, a register, or a
memory location; the destination operand can be a register or a memory location. (However, two memory oper-
ands cannot be used in one instruction.) Each bit of the result is 1 if the corresponding bits of the operands are
different; each bit is 0 if the corresponding bits are the same.
This instruction can be used with a LOCK prefix to allow the instruction to be executed atomically.
Opcode
Instruction
Op/
En
64-Bit
Mode
Compat/
Leg Mode
Description
34 ib
XOR AL, imm8
I
Valid
Valid
AL XOR imm8.
35 iw
XOR AX, imm16
I
Valid
Valid
AX XOR imm16.
35 id
XOR EAX, imm32
I
Valid
Valid
EAX XOR imm32.
REX.W + 35 id
XOR RAX, imm32
I
Valid
N.E.
RAX XOR imm32 (sign-extended).
80 /6 ib
XOR r/m8, imm8
MI
Valid
Valid
r/m8 XOR imm8.
REX + 80 /6 ib
XOR r/m8*, imm8
MI
Valid
N.E.
r/m8 XOR imm8.
81 /6 iw
XOR r/m16, imm16
MI
Valid
Valid
r/m16 XOR imm16.
81 /6 id
XOR r/m32, imm32
MI
Valid
Valid
r/m32 XOR imm32.
REX.W + 81 /6 id
XOR r/m64, imm32
MI
Valid
N.E.
r/m64 XOR imm32 (sign-extended).
83 /6 ib
XOR r/m16, imm8
MI
Valid
Valid
r/m16 XOR imm8 (sign-extended).
83 /6 ib
XOR r/m32, imm8
MI
Valid
Valid
r/m32 XOR imm8 (sign-extended).
REX.W + 83 /6 ib
XOR r/m64, imm8
MI
Valid
N.E.
r/m64 XOR imm8 (sign-extended).
30 /r
XOR r/m8, r8
MR
Valid
Valid
r/m8 XOR r8.
REX + 30 /r
XOR r/m8*, r8*
MR
Valid
N.E.
r/m8 XOR r8.
31 /r
XOR r/m16, r16
MR
Valid
Valid
r/m16 XOR r16.
31 /r
XOR r/m32, r32
MR
Valid
Valid
r/m32 XOR r32.
REX.W + 31 /r
XOR r/m64, r64
MR
Valid
N.E.
r/m64 XOR r64.
32 /r
XOR r8, r/m8
RM
Valid
Valid
r8 XOR r/m8.
REX + 32 /r
XOR r8*, r/m8*
RM
Valid
N.E.
r8 XOR r/m8.
33 /r
XOR r16, r/m16
RM
Valid
Valid
r16 XOR r/m16.
33 /r
XOR r32, r/m32
RM
Valid
Valid
r32 XOR r/m32.
REX.W + 33 /r
XOR r64, r/m64
RM
Valid
N.E.
r64 XOR r/m64.
NOTES:
* In 64-bit mode, r/m8 can not be encoded to access the following byte registers if a REX prefix is used: AH, BH, CH, DH.
Op/En
Operand 1
Operand 2
Operand 3
Operand 4
I
AL/AX/EAX/RAX
imm8/16/32
NA
NA
MI
ModRM:r/m (r, w)
imm8/16/32
NA
NA
MR
ModRM:r/m (r, w)
ModRM:reg (r)
NA
NA
RM
ModRM:reg (r, w)
ModRM:r/m (r)
NA
NA
XOR—Logical Exclusive OR
INSTRUCTION SET REFERENCE, V-Z
5-624 Vol. 2C
In 64-bit mode, using a REX prefix in the form of REX.R permits access to additional registers (R8-R15). Using a
REX prefix in the form of REX.W promotes operation to 64 bits. See the summary chart at the beginning of this
section for encoding data and limits.
Operation
DEST := DEST XOR SRC;
Flags Affected
The OF and CF flags are cleared; the SF, ZF, and PF flags are set according to the result. The state of the AF flag is
undefined.
Protected Mode Exceptions
#GP(0)
If the destination operand points to a non-writable segment.
If a memory operand effective address is outside the CS, DS, ES, FS, or GS segment limit.
If the DS, ES, FS, or GS register contains a NULL segment selector.
#SS(0)
If a memory operand effective address is outside the SS segment limit.
#PF(fault-code)
If a page fault occurs.
#AC(0)
If alignment checking is enabled and an unaligned memory reference is made while the
current privilege level is 3.
#UD
If the LOCK prefix is used but the destination is not a memory operand.
Real-Address Mode Exceptions
#GP
If a memory operand effective address is outside the CS, DS, ES, FS, or GS segment limit.
#SS
If a memory operand effective address is outside the SS segment limit.
#UD
If the LOCK prefix is used but the destination is not a memory operand.
Virtual-8086 Mode Exceptions
#GP(0)
If a memory operand effective address is outside the CS, DS, ES, FS, or GS segment limit.
#SS(0)
If a memory operand effective address is outside the SS segment limit.
#PF(fault-code)
If a page fault occurs.
#AC(0)
If alignment checking is enabled and an unaligned memory reference is made.
#UD
If the LOCK prefix is used but the destination is not a memory operand.
Compatibility Mode Exceptions
Same exceptions as in protected mode.
64-Bit Mode Exceptions
#SS(0)
If a memory address referencing the SS segment is in a non-canonical form.
#GP(0)
If the memory address is in a non-canonical form.
#PF(fault-code)
If a page fault occurs.
#AC(0)
If alignment checking is enabled and an unaligned memory reference is made while the
current privilege level is 3.
#UD
If the LOCK prefix is used but the destination is not a memory operand.
